Guide to the Ballitore Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Ballitore papers
1756-1889
OSB MSS 50
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.5
(7 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, mainly between members of the Leadbeater family, including Mary Leadbeater and her husband William, and the Shackleton family, including Mary Leadbeater's parents, Elizabeth and Richard Shackleton, her sister, Sarah, and her grandfather, Abraham Shackleton. There is also correspondence with many other relatives, including Mary's cousin, Margaret Pike. Many letters were written by children. There is extensive correspondence between Mary and the poet Melesina Trench. The papers also include poetry by Mary (including a poem written about Edmund Burke); narrative diaries kept by her mother, Elizabeth; manuscript magazines written by children; and a family tree.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Richard Shackleton
Richard Shackleton succeeded his father, Abraham, as master of Ballitore School, a Quaker school that opened in 1726 in Ballitore, Ireland. One of Abraham's students had been Edmund Burke. Richard's second wife was Elizabeth Carleton, and Mary Shackleton Leadbeater was their daughter.
Mary Shackleton Leadbeater
Mary Shackleton Leadbeater married William Leadbeater (a former student at the Ballitore School) in 1791. They resided in Ballitore, where he was a farmer and landowner, and she ran the village post office. In 1794, she published anonymously "Extracts and Original Anecdotes for the Improvement of Youth." She also published "Poems" in 1808; "Cottage Dialogues among the Irish Peasantry" in 1811; and "Memoirs and Letters of Richard and Elizabeth Shackleton" in 1822. Her "Annals of Ballitore" was printed posthumously in 1862 by Richard Davis Webb as "The Leadbeater Papers."
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, mainly between members of the Leadbeater family, including Mary Shackleton Leadbeater and her husband William, and members of the Shackleton family. There is also correspondence with many other relatives, including Mary's cousin, Margaret Pike; a number of letters were written by children. There is extensive correspondence between Mary and the poet Melesina Trench. The papers also include poetry by Mary (including a poem written about Edmund Burke); narrative diaries kept by her mother, Elizabeth; manuscript magazines written by children; and a family tree.
Arrangement
Organized into 1 series: I. Correspondence and Other Papers, 1709-1827.
Children's writings; Education -- Ireland; English literature -- 18th century; English literature -- 19th century; Families -- Ireland -- Domestic relations; Female friendship; Irish literature -- 18th century; Irish literature -- 19th century; Quakers; Quakers -- Education; Society of Friends -- Ireland; Women authors, English; Women authors, Irish; Ballitore (Ireland); Ireland -- Social life and customs -- 18th century; Ireland -- Social life and customs -- 19th century; Burke, Edmund, 1729-1797; Leadbeater, Mary, 1758-1826; Leadbeater, William, ca. 1757-1827; Ledbetter family; Pike, Margaret; Shackleton, Abraham, 1696-1771; Shackleton, Elizabeth, 1726-1804; Shackleton family; Shackleton, Richard, 1726-1792; Shackleton, Sarah; Trench, Melesina Chenevix St. George, 1768-1827; Ballitore School
- Correspondence and Other Papers, 1709-1827; Series I; 2.5; (7 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Alphabetically arranged, with unsorted material at the end of the series.
  The series contains mostly family correspondence, mainly between members of the Leadbeater family, including Mary Leadbeater and her husband William, and the Shackleton family, including Mary Leadbeater's parents, Elizabeth and Richard Shackleton, her sister, Sarah, and her grandfather, Abraham Shackleton. There is also correspondence with many other relatives, including Mary's cousin, Margaret Pike. Many letters were written by children.
  Frequent topics of the correspondence include personal and family news, particularly of the heath of various family members; business matters; Ballitore School; Ireland; and literature and poetry. There is extensive correspondence between Mary and the poet Melesina Trench, in which the two women discuss literature and their writings.
  The papers also include poetry by Mary, including a poem written about Edmund Burke; narrative diaries kept by her mother, Elizabeth; manuscript magazines written by children; and a family tree.
  Scope and Contents
  Detailed folder notes in the box and folder list highlight the main topics of many correspondents' letters.
  - Bibliographic Materials (Box 1)
  - Biographical / Bibliographical Papers (Box 1)
  - Burton, Charles. ALS to Mary Leadbeater, Ballyboy, 1825 March (Box 1)
    Letter discusses farming.
  - Carleton, Deborah. 2 ALS to Mary Leadbeater, Ballitore, 1774 May, 1778 May (Box 1)
    Letters discuss personal matters.
  - Carleton, Joshua. 10 ALS to George Rooke, Dublin, 1709 January -1709 August (Box 1)
  - Christy, James. 13 ALS to various persons, [v.p.], 1781 January -1799 January; 2 (Box 1)
    Includes 5 letters from Deb[orah] Christy and 2 from Mary Christy. Letters are addressed to Richard Shackleton, Mary and William Leadbeater and Thomas Chandlee.
  - Colles, Edward. ALS to Mary Leadbeater, Liverpool, 1823 September (Box 1)
    Letter discusses personal matters.
  - Coote, Charles, d. 1770. 34 ALS to Mary Leadbeater, [v.p.], 1779 March -1820 October; 4 (Box 1)
    The letters discuss personal matters and include portions of Coote's verse, the inscription on the tomb of his daughter Mary Ann, and detail about the school he attended. The death of Charles, 4th Duke of Rutland, is mentioned, 1787 Oct 26, and problems of publishing one of Mary Leadbeater's books in London are discussed, 1812 Apr 16.
  - Coote, Charles, 1761-1835. 2 ALS to an unnamed recipient, Dublin, [n.p.], 1809 January 20, 1821 March 26 (Box 1)
  - Costello, Mary. 14 ALS to Mary Leadbeater, [v.p.], circa 1812-1819; 2 (Box 1)
    Letters discuss personal matters, Mrs. Leadbeater's poems and the Ballitore School.
  - Diary, 1832-1833 (Box 1)
    Anonymous manuscript. Mentions a cholera plague, politics, especially the "soap question", India, and family life.
  - Grattan, Catherine. 10 ALS to William Leadbeater, [v.p.], 1819 February - 1823 May (Box 1)
    Letters discuss Catherine Grattan's employment as a teacher.
  - Grattan, Eliza[beth]. 9 ALS to William Leadbeater, [v.p.], 1814 November -1823 April (Box 1)
  - Grattan, Francis. 2 ALS to William Leadbeater, [n.p.], 1822 September, 1824 May (Box 1)
    Letters discuss personal matters including the death of Henry Grattan and some poems written by him.
  - Grattan, Richard. 15 ALS to Mary Leadbeater, [v.p.], 1808-1819 (Box 1)
    Includes 8 letters from Eleanor Grattan and 1 letter from John Grattan.
  - Halpin, D. 3 ALS to Mary Leadbeater, Rathangan, 1 [n.p.], 1825 October,undated (Box 1)
  - Leadbeater, Deborah
    - 45 ALS to Elizabeth Leadbeater, [v.p.], 1803 August-1820 January (Box 2)
      Letters discuss personal matters, especially health. Included are several postscripts by Mary Leadbeater and several poems.
    - 54 ALS to Elizabeth Leadbeater, [v.p.], 1808 April-1816 November (Box 2)
      Letters discuss general matters, health, Mary Leadbeater's Cottage Dialogues, 1811 Sep 10, and a comet. Includes a postscript by Mary Leadbeater and several pages of verse by Deborah Leadbeater.
  - Leadbeater, Dorothy. ALS to Mary Leadbeater, Mountmelick, 1811 January (Box 2)
    Letter discusses general and personal matter.
  - Leadbeater, Edward, [v.p.]
    - ALS to "Uncle", 1802 November (Box 2)
    - ALS to "Uncle", 1803 September (Box 2)
    - ALS to "Uncle", 1809 January (Box 2)
  - Leadbeater, Elizabeth. 2 ALS to William Leadbeater, Ballitore, Mountmelick, 1801 April, 1806 August (Box 2)
  - Leadbeater, Henry
    - 3 ALS to Mary Leadbeater, Coote Hill, 1791 January-1804 December (Box 2)
      Henry Leadbeater, a physician, provides several medical opinions.
    - 2 ALS to William Leadbeater, Coote Hill, 1799 December, 1805 April (Box 2)
      Discusses illnesses which were making Henry an invalid.
    - ALS to Abraham Shackleton, Coote Hill, 1803 February 1 (Box 2)
      Proposed visit by Leadbeater to Ballitore is discussed.
    - 10 ALS to unnamed recipient, Coote Hill, 1790 October-1809 June (Box 2)
      The letters discuss business concerns, especially Henry Leadbeater's linen trade.
    - 4 ALS to an unnamed recipient, Coote Hill, 1791 September-1798 January (Box 2)
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1797 December (Box 2)
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1802 March (Box 2)
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, 1803 April (Box 2)
  - Leadbeater, John. ALS to Rev. Ephraim Harper, Snugborough, 1772 July 30 (Box 2)
  - Leadbeater, Mary (Shackleton), 1758-1826
    - ALS to Deborah Carleton, Clonmel, 1778 May 23 (Box 2)
      Describes trip that Mary Shackleton and her mother took through parts of England.
    - ALS to Richard Grattan, [Ballitore], undated (Box 2)
      Includes short note from Grattan on verso.
    - ALS to Ephraim Harper, 1808 December (Box 2)
    - ALS to Elizabeth Leadbeater, Ballitore, 1812 July 16 (Box 2)
    - 38 ALS to William Leadbeater, [v.p.], 1792 June-1824 October; 4 (Box 2)
      Poetry is included with the letters.
    - 3 ALS to Mary Nicholson, Ballitore, 1780 January-1784 April (Box 2)
    - ALS (copy) to Thomas L. O'Beirne, Ballitore, 1802 February (Box 2)
      Letter deals with Edmund Burke including several anecdotes.
    - 8 ALS to Elizabeth Shackleton, [v.p.], 1780 June-1789 January (Box 2)
      Letters discuss general and personal matters, Mary Leadbeater's impressions of London, details of a Quaker meeting, and Samuel Neale.
    - 17 ALS to Richard Shackleton, [v.p.], 1781 February-1791 April; 2 (Box 2)
      Letters discuss personal matters. Included is an account of a duel; meeting of an American; and mention of Edmund Burke with a quote from him and on his stand towards slavery, 1783 Aug 6, 1789 May 30. Also postscripts by Abraham Shackleton, H[enry] Tuke and Sarah Shackleton are included.
    - 47 ALS to Melesina Trench, [v.p.], 1802 June-1827 July; 5 (Box 2)
      Letters discuss literary matters and include several poems.
    - Letter (copy of extract) to an unnamed recipient, [n.p.], 1784 September 7 (Box 2)
      Letter discusses Edmund Burke.
    - Uncat., 2 (Box 3)
    - Poems (holograph, signed), [n.p.], undated (Box 3)
      Poem titles are: "To Edmund Burke"; "On Butler's Court"; "To Jane Burke."
    - Verses (holograph, signed), [1780 or later] (Box 3)
      Consists of 3 poems, "On Butler's Court" (partly composed by Richard Shackleton), "To Jane Burke", and "To Edmund Burke".
    - Written on occasion of a report that the only son of Edmund Burke was lost at sea (holograph poem, signed), [n.p.] (Box 3)
  - Leadbeater, William, ca. 1757-1827
    - ALS to Henry Leadbeater, Mountmellick, 1789 Aug (Box 3)
    - ALS to Abraham Shackleton, Mountmellick, 1787 Mar (Box 3)
    - ALS to an unnamed recipient, [n.p.], 1794 Feb 23 (Box 3)
    - "Essay on Charity" (holograph, signed), [n.p.], [ca. 1775] (Box 3)
    - Memorandum (holograph, initialed), [n.p.], 1793 (Box 3)
      Describing a visit of Job Scott to Ballycane, July 1793.
    - ALS to John Leadbeater, 1791 November (Box 3)
    - ALS to Alexander McMullen, 1803 March (Box 3)
    - ALS to "Edward", 1803 September (Box 3)
  - "Letters on the Character Situation of the Irish Peasantry", [n.p.], undated (Box 3)
    Anonymous manuscript.
  - Medlicott, Sarah. 2 ALS to Mary Leadbeater, [n.p.], 1812 February (Box 3)
  - "Notes respecting the last illness &gc. of Job Scott", [n.p.], undated (Box 3)
  - Palmer, Sanford. 2 ALS., 1815 (Box 3)
  - Pike, Ann. 2 ALS to Mary Leadbeater, Dublin, 1788 September, December (Box 3)
  - Pike, Jonathon. ALS to Mary Leadbeater, Dublin, 1789 August (Box 3)
  - Pike, Margaret. 63 ALS to Mary Leadbeater, [v.p.], 1786 February-1826 June; 7 (Box 3)
    Letters discuss deaths and illnesses. Also included are comments on Annals of Ballitore, 1808 Apr 20; Cottage dialogues, 1812 Dec 26; Melesina Trench, 1816 Dec 23; and the Rebellion of 1798, 1798 Jun 29.
  - Pike, Richard. ALS to Mary Leadbeater, Dublin, 1787 December (Box 3)
  - Pike, William. ALS to Mary Leadbeater, Brookfield, 1788 April (Box 3)
  - Rice, Eliza. 8 ALS to Mary Leadbeater, [v.p.], 1809 December-1810 December (Box 3)
  - Rooke, George, 1652-1742
    - 30 ALS to Joshua Carleton, [v.p.], 1709 March-1731 July; 4 (Box 3)
      Letters discuss personal matters. Two references are made to the Duke of Marlborough, 1712 Aug 25.
    - ALS to Robert Strettell, [n.p.], 1709 April 28 (Box 3)
    - 7 ALS to various persons, [v.p.], 1712-1736 (Box 3)
      Letters include 2 to Timothy Forbes; 1 to Joshua Carleton; 1 to Joan Rooke, his mother; 2 to George Rooke, his father; and 1 to William Westbury.
  - Shackleton, Abraham, 1697-1771. ALS to Mary Leadbeater, Dublin, 1769 August (Box 3)
    Letter is from grandfather to granddaughter giving his blessing and recognizing her writing ability.
  - Shackleton, Deborah. 31 ALS to Elizabeth Leadbeater, [v.p.], 1811 February-1824 July; 4 (Box 3)
  - Shackleton, Eben
    - 20 ALS to Elizabeth Leadbeater, [v.p.], 1807 March-1823 April; 2 (Box 3)
      Letters discuss general matters including comment on the poor and Roman Catholics.
    - ALS to Sarah Shackleton, Liverpool, 1806 February (Box 3)
  - Shackleton, Elizabeth (Carleton), 1726-1804
    - AL to Deborah Carleton, Ballitore, [1757] October (Box 4)
    - ALS to Rachel Carleton, Ballitore, 1755 October (Box 4)
    - 7 ALS to Mary Leadbeater, Ballitore, Dublin, 1771 November-1789 May (Box 4)
      Letters discuss personal matters and Quaker meetings, especially funerals. Includes a postscript written by Sarah Shackleton.
    - 118 ALS to Elizabeth Pike, mostly Ballitore, 1753 October-1762 June; 12 (Box 4)
      Letters discuss personal matters. Included are several postscripts by Richard Shackleton.
    - 49 ALS to Elizabeth Pike, Ballitore, 1762 August-1769 December; 5 (Box 4)
      Letters discuss personal matters. Included are postscripts by Richard Shackleton.
    - 26 ALS to Richard Shackleton, [v.p.], 1758 October-1780 September; 3 (Box 4)
      Letters discuss illnesses, Quaker meetings and Richard Shackleton's living with Edmund Burke.
    - Diary (holograph, signed), 1753-1763 (Box 4)
      Relates travels to various Quaker meetings.
  - Shackleton, Richard, 1728-1792
    - 3 ALS to Deborah Carleton, Ballitore, 1763 July-August (Box 4)
    - ALS to Deborah Carleton, Ballitore, 1777 July (Box 4)
    - 2 ALS to Rachel Carleton, Ballitore, 1775 December, 1776 March (Box 4)
    - 78 ALS (initialed) to Mary Leadbeater, [v.p.], 1773 November-1792 August; 9 (Box 4)
      Letters discuss general matters pertaining to Quakers in England. Interesting references to Edmund Burke and George Crabbe.
    - AL (initialed) to William Leadbeater, Lurgan, 1791 April (Box 5)
      Discusses family and Quaker matters.
    - ALS to Elizabeth Pike, Ballitore, 1756 August (Box 5)
      Letter discusses the selling of a horse.
    - 61 ALS to Elizabeth Shackleton, [v.p.], 1756 May-1790 November; 7 (Box 5)
      Letters discuss personal matters and Quakers. References are made to Edmund Burke.
    - 2 ALS to Sally Shackleton, Ballitore, 1784 September 3, 1789 August 16 (Box 5)
    - ALS to unnamed recipient, Ballitore, 1757 April 3 (Box 5)
      The death and funeral of a friend's wife.
  - Shackleton, Sarah
    - 150 ALS to Mary Leadbeater, [v.p.], 1783 June-1824 February; 15 (Box 5)
      Letters discuss personal matters. Several postscripts by other family members are included, as well as poems by Sarah Shackelton and a letter written by Gustavius Vassa [Olaudah Equiano] to the Society of Friends thanking them for publishing A Caution to Gt. Brit. and her Colonies.
    - 6 ALS to William Leadbeater, [v.p.], 1798 February-1809 August (Box 5)
    - 7 ALS to Elizabeth Shackleton, [v.p.], 1793 August-1798 September (Box 5)
      Letters discuss personal matters related to Quaker Meetings: Sarah Shackleton traveled throughout England meeting Quakers, among them George Rooke.
    - 9 ALS to Richard Shackleton, [v.p.], 1786 January-1792 February (Box 5)
    - Uncat. (Box 5)
  - Thompson, Abigail. 3 ALS to Richard Shackleton, [v.p.], 1761-1785 (Box 5)
    Includes 1 letter from Deborah Thompson.
  - Trench, Melesina (Chenevix), 1768-1827. ca. 300 ALS to Mary Leadbeater, [v.p.], 1802 June-1827 July; 3 (Box 6)
    Several letters from Melesina Trench's family are included; one notes the death of Melesina Trench. Letters discuss literary matters, especially concerning the works of Mary Leadbeater and Melesina Trench. Several poems are included throughout the letters.
  - Two folders of unsorted journals and essays., 2 (Box 7)
    Inlcudes various copied exercises, quotations, and verses, along with a family pedigree chart and other papers.
  - Two folders of unsorted journals, essays, and fragments., 2 (Box 7)
    Includes two accounts of redirected letters, various handwritten and printed childrens' exercises, and other personal lists and papers.
  - One folder of unsorted letters. (Box 7)
  - One folder of unsorted letters and fragments. (Box 7)